While JPEG is the most important image compression algorithm, and as we
我们讲过 JPEG (静止图像压缩标准) 是最重要的图像压缩算法
discussed before, probably the most important image processing algorithm
大概也是最重要的图像处理算法
overall, there are other techniques for image and video compression which are
总体上说 还有其他一些非常重要的图像和视频压缩技术
very important. And I want to describe the basic
而我想阐述的是
underlying, the concepts behind two of them.
在这两者背后隐含的基本概念
One is JPEG-LS, and the other is MPEG. JPEG-LS basically permits us to compress
其中一个是JPEG-LS (无损图像压缩标准) 另外一个是MPEG (动态图像压缩标准)
lossless, basically without any loss of information, preserving exactly the pixel
JPEG-LS允许我们进行无损压缩 也就是说不会有任何信息损失
value at every single pixel in the image. An MPEG is the one that we use to
图像中的每一个像素值都会被保留 而MPEG则是我们用来压缩视频的标准
compress video, and you probably have MPEG in your mobile
大家的手机中大概都有MPEG
phones as well, and you have seen videos on the internet
并且大家在网络上都看过用MPEG压缩的视频
that are compressed with MPEG. So let's describe the underlying concept
那么下面就来讲解
between these two very important image and video compressing, image and video
这两个非常重要的图像和视频压缩技术
procession techniques as what? And we're going to start with JPEG-LS
背后的概念 我们先从JPEG-LS的概念开始讲起
concepts, basically. And the idea behind that is what's called
在这一标准背后的思想叫做
predictive lossless compression. So for comparison, I left here the basic
无损预测压缩 为了对比 我在这里放了
diagram that we have seen so many times already for JPEG-LS,
我们已经多次见过的 JPEG-LS基本流程图
while this is the basic diagram for predictive coding.
而这边的则是预测编码的基本流程图
And the basic idea of predictive coding is very, very simple.
预测编码的基本思想非常非常简单
It's even simpler than the idea of JPEG. And let's just illustrate that with an
甚至比JPEG的都要简单 让我来举个例子说明一下
example. We're just draw a small portion of an
把我画的当做一幅图像的一小部分
image. And, in predictive coding, the first
在预测编码中
thing that we have to define, is an order.
我们首先需要确立顺序
We're going to compress one pixel after another.
我们将对像素逐个进行压缩
And, let's say that we define what's called, a roster order, that we basically
假设我们采用一种叫做光栅扫描顺序的方法
go from left to right, and we'll encode the first row, then we code, the second
按照从左至右的顺序 先对第一行编码 然后是第二行
row, and we keep going. So let's say that we have encoded
依次进行 假设我们已经完成之前所有的编码
everything and now we need to encode this pixel.
然后现在要对这个像素编码
The idea of predictive coding is to guess, to predict the value of this pixel
预测编码的思想就是根据以前的像素值来猜想和预测
based only on the past. We cannot predict it based on the future
后面的像素值 我们不能依据未来的像素值去预测
because the decoder doesn't know the future.
因为解码器并不知道未来的情况
That the caller has only received all this pictures.
而调用者所能接收到的只有这些像素
So we could, for example say, okay, I'm going to guess, I'm going to predict that
所以我们只能 比方说 好吧 我来猜测一下
the value of this pixel is identical to the value of the previous pixel.
这个像素的值可能与前一个像素相同
And then what we do is, after we do the prediction, we basically compute the
在预测之后 我们需要来计算
error, between my prediction and the actual value.
预测值和真实值之间的误差
And what we encode, let's say with Huffman coding here, is the error.
然后我们只需要将误差进行编码 比如这里使用了霍夫曼编码
And the decoder basically is going to emulate what the encoder is doing.
而解码器就将模拟编码器所做的
It's basically going to say, okay, I'm going to do the same prediction.
也就是说 好吧 那我也来做和你一样的预测
That you did. I know the past, exactly as you know it,
我也像你一样知道过去的情况
and I'm going to predict that this pixel, with this value, so the color and the
我会用这个值来预测这个像素
color talk with each other. They are using exactly the same
所以编码器和解码器互相交流 它们在使用完全相同的预测策略
prediction strategy. So, I predicted this one, and you gave me
那么 我预测这个 你给我误差
the error. I basically add to my prediction the
然后我直接在预测上加上误差
error, and I have this pixel value. And then I continue to the next pixel.
于是我得到了这个像素值 然后我继续到下一个像素
I do exactly the same. Process.
依旧采用完全相同的方法
And the basic idea is that if you are very good at predicting this error is
基本思想就是如果你的预测精准
going to be very close to zero, all the time.
那么误差就总是会非常接近于零
It's not going to have any possible value.
这个误差并不会是随机的值
It's going to have values around zero, and that's exactly if you remember what
而会是近似于零的值 如果你还记得的话
encoders like Huffman coding likes. To have values that appear a lot, so we
这正是像霍夫曼编码器那样 给经常出现的值
can give a very short code to them, and some values, once in a while you're
赋予一个很短的编码 而时不时会有
going to make a big mistake in your prediction.
一些值在预测中产生较大的错误
Don't worry, because you're going to encode error,
这时候别担心 因为后面将编码误差
and basically when, by encoding the error, you're going to
通过将误差编码
have lossless compression. So once in a while you make a big
我们会得到无损压缩 所以当偶尔产生了一个大错误
mistake. Then Huffman will use a larger code for
霍夫曼编码将对其赋予一个较长的编码
that mistake, but because that happens once and awhile, it won't be so
但是因为这只是偶尔发生
problematic, and your going to be able to still compress.
所以并不会成问题 而之后依旧能够进行压缩
So, a lot of the art in predictive lossless compression is in designing, in
所以 无损预测压缩的很多技术关键都在于预测器的设计
designing your predictor. Such that the error is as small as
为了使得误差总是尽可能的小
possible all the time. Hopefully, zero.
甚至希望是零误差
If you're great in predicting, it's going to be always zero.
如果你的预测精准 那误差几乎总是零
And it's going to be able to compress a lot.
这样可以大量压缩
But at least it's going to be very, very close to zero if you're doing smart
如果你的预测器足够智能 至少将非常非常接近于零
predictors. And then the decoder is going to just do
然后解码器将只是做一个非常非常简单的解码
a very, very simple decoding. So know that overall this structure of a
这样总体上来说 这个无损预测压缩技术的结构
predictive lossless compression technique is a bit simpler than the one of JPEG.
比JPEG的要稍简单一些
Ofcourse it's not going to be able to achieve as much compression.
当然这并不能达到如此大量的压缩
Base is going to be lossless which is very important.
但最重要的是原图像将是无损的
So lets just illustrate a couple of possible.
下面我来举例说明几个可行的预测器
Predictors. So we have our image.
这是我们的图像
An. We're going to, basically, drop the
下面 我们来画一下预测器
liters, again, let us see that all these have been encoded.
像以前一样 假设前面这些都已经被编码了
And lets just consider now, that what I want to do is predict, this pixel.
现在来考虑一下 我想对这个像素进行预测
So, one thing I can do, is predict it based on the past.
那么我们可以基于过去进行预测
Just on this pixel. So I can say that I predict this to be F
只是基于这个像素 也就是说
of X minus one Y, and then, if I'm the encoder, I'm going to take actual F of
预测它为F(x-1,y) 然后编码器用实际值F(x,y)
XY. I'm going to substract, so my error at
减去预测值 所以对于这一像素的误差将会是
this pixel will be F. Of X minus one, Y minus F.
F(x-1,y) - F(x,y)
Xy. And this what I'm going to basically save
这就是我要通过霍夫曼编码保存的值
through half my coding. And then once again the decoder is
就像之前说的 此时解码器将模拟预测器
going to emulate my predictor, it's going to say oh you predicted this, you
它会说 啊 你预测了这个
gave me an error, I add the error to my prediction, I get this pixel value.
你给了我一个误差 那我将误差加到我的预测中 就可以得到这个像素的值
Very, very simple operation, in particular for the decoder, it's a, it's
非常非常简单的运算过程 特别是对于解码器来说
a really, really simple operation. So, one possible predictor is just to use
这是一个相当简单的运算 所以可以用前一个像素作为一种可行的预测器
the past. Another is basically to use the two
而另一种是通过前面两个像素来预测
previous pixels. Let's say an average of the three, two
比如说可以用前面两个像素的平均值
Some other predictors, like, for example
还有其他一些预测器 比如JPEG-LS
JPEG-LS, we'll actually consider a bit more.
所考虑的范围就更广一些
We'll basically try to use, be a bit smarter, and maybe use all this
需要更智能一些 或许会试图利用这个区域所有的值
region. Say, okay,
可能大家会问
why only to use the one on the left? Maybe I can also use the one on top of
为什么只使用左边这些呢？ 或许我可以使用上面这个
you, and the one basically diagonal. And, you can do normal combinations of
还有对角上的这个 所有这些合理的组合都可以
them. As I say, you could, if you were to use
像之前说过的 我们可以这样
these two, you could basically average them.
如果想使用这两个 那我们可以直接平均一下
You can also average these three. Actually JPEG-LS does a bit more
也可以平均这三个 事实上JPEG-LS采用了更复杂的方法
elaborated technique. So JPEG-LS is the standard for lossless
总之  JPEG-LS是无损图像压缩的一个标准
image compression. It's actually the algorithm that is in
事实上它正是火星车上所采用的算法
the Mars rovers. One of the algorithms that, that are in
在火星车上用于图像压缩的算法之一
the Mars rovers for image compression is JPEG-LS and it has.
就包括更智能一些的JPEG-LS
a bit smarter. It tries to find basically where edges
它会尝试找出图像的边缘
are in the image. But it's also are very simple, remember
但它仍然是非常简单的
compression has to be simple in order to become a standard, so that everybody can
记住 压缩要成为标准就必须要简单易行
implement them and they can run very fast.
这样才能被所有人运用 并且快速地执行
And we have seen that concept appear already in JPEG.
我们已经在JPEG中了解过这一概念
It also appears in JPEG-LS, and it will appear as well in MPEG.
它对于JPEG-LS也同样适用 而且也将在MPEG中再次出现
So you could use this region. Basically you could use as I said the
其实就像我说过的
whole past. You could basically say I'm going to
大家可以使用所有过去的区域 也可以只使用这些像素
write to use only these pixels. maybe if I have encoded already, if I'm
如果已经对这些进行过编码
in the middle of a very large image, I could basically use my whole pass,
假设这是一张非常大的图像中央 我就可以使用
past data, all the way to here.
所有过去的值 一直到这里
The problem is that if you do that, you're going to have to remember a lot of
问题是 如果要这么做的话 就必须记住很多的像素值
pixels, it's going to take a lot of memory, if you just used everything in
而这将占用大量内存 如果你要使用过去的所有信息
the past, it's just too much. So JPEG-LS has most modern predictive
那实在是太多了 所以JPEG-LS有着最现代化的
lossless compression techniques. This is, may be the previous role, at
无损预测压缩技术 也就是说可能只使用前一行
most two roles before, but not much more than that.
或者至多前两行 但不会超过这些了
Otherwise, SSA becomes too complex and too much memory.
否则串行存储体系 (SSA) 将会非常复杂 并且占用大量内存
So, that's basically the idea of predictive coding.
以上就是预测编码的基本思想
Now let's see how effective this is with just a very simple image.
现在来看看对于一张很简单的图像它预测效果如何
So this is a nice image from earth, taken from outer space.
这是一张不错的从外太空拍摄的地球图像
And this is a distribution. Remember we talked about histograms.
这是一个我们之前提到过的分布直方图
This is the distribution of pixel values. Okay?
表达了像素值的分布 还记得吗？
So you see Huffman might like this because there are some concentration of
霍夫曼编码可能会喜欢这样 因为有一定量的
pixel values around 150, but there is still a very, very wide distribution.
像素值都在150左右 但是它仍然有一个非常非常宽的分布
Now if we do predictive coding with one of the predictors I just mentioned.
现在我们用之前讲过的预测器来做预测编码
So we go roster like this and at every point we basically predict the value
我们像这样一行一行地扫描每个点
based on some very small neighborhood around that value.
并根据它周边几个点的值来预测这个点的值
Then the error is distributed as here. So we predict, we compute the error as I've
这样产生的误差分布如这张图所示 用先前讲到的方法计算误差
shown in the previous slide, and we plot the distribution of error, the histogram.
然后画出误差分布的直方图
But look how nice it is, it's a smart predictor and it's a relatively nice
这是一种好的预测器和一幅好的图像 所以得到很好的误差图
image. And then we basically get a strong
这样得到的误差会集中到零附近
concentration around zero, and you can observe here a plot of the prediction
大家可以看到这是预测误差图
error and as expected when then are big changes,
就像预期那样 当图像中出现大的改变时
your prediction doesn't know that a change is about to happen. So that's
预测器并不会知道变化的发生
where you make most of the mistakes. In regions that are relatively uniform,
这就是大多数错误产生的区域 而在灰度值相对均匀的区域
you don't make a lot of mistakes, so that's why you get a lot of zeros.
预测器不会产生太多的错误 这就是分布图中有很多零的原因
And okay, once in a while, there's a big change you make a mistake and Huffman is
由于图像中偶尔出现的大的改变 因此产生了预测误差
going to take more bits to represent that prediction error, but that happens once
霍夫曼编码将用更多的比特来表示这个误差 但这种情况仅仅是偶尔出现
in a while. So most of your errors of the prediction
因此大多数预测误差都会很小
are very small, and that's really, really good.
这样对编码极为有利
So that's basically the underlying idea of JPEG-LS, or any predictive lossless
这些就是JPEG-LS背后的思想 任何一种预测无损编码器
encoder or compression. Now, you can add quantization as well.
无损压缩的思想也是如此 你也可以将量化加入到
In a predictive coding, or in a predictive image compression technique.
预测编码或相应的图像压缩技术中
So basically you quantize the error. The same way that we saw how to quantize
我们将用量化变换系数的方法
transform coefficients, you quantize the error.
来量化误差
And with that, you can achieve more compression.
这样就能够实现更多的压缩
You can actually have control on how much error.
事实上 误差大小是可以被控制的
So if you are allowing +-plus minus 1 pixel value of error, of quantization in
如果每个像素点的值在量化时都可以有正负一的误差
your error, then you know that your reconstructed
那么重建后的图像
image will differ, will differ from the original image only
它每个点的灰度值和原图就会仅仅相差正负一
by +-plus minus 1 grey value. So you can have a lot of control.
这样就能很好地控制误差的范围
Because you're not working the transform domain,
因为这不是对变换域进行量化
you're working the image domain. And that's also part of JPEG-LS,
而是对图像域进行量化 JPEG-LS就用到了这种方法
that you can add quantization to your errors.
来对误差进行量化
basically, the decoder will receive a quantized error, and will reproduce a
解码器得到的是量化后的误差值
pixel that has a small variation compared to the original pixel.
重新生成的像素点与原来的相比 会有小小的变化
One very important thing to have in mind is that when you introduce quantization,
下面这一点很重要 大家一定要记住 如果引进量化
you have to do your prediction based on the quantized error. So let's just do the
预测时使用的则是量化后的误差 我们来画一下之前那张图
same drawing that we had before. If we are going to predict this pixel
如果我们要预测这个像素点
based on this one, then remember,
根据这个像素点 那么请记住
the decoder is going to only have the quantized version of that after it has
解码器在重建量化误差之后 只会有这个像素量化后的值
reconstructed the quantized error. So at the encoder, you have to also
对于编码器而言 它必须要模仿解码器的行为
emulate what the decoder is doing and consider only the quantized version of
并按照量化后的像素值计算
your pixel. If you were to predict based on the
如果是基于原图进行预测
original version, then you're predicting based on something that the decoder
则是在用解码器无法获取的信息做预测
doesn't have. And that's why it's the quantized value
因此 在流程图里
that enters the area of the predictor in this drawing.
进入预测器中的是量化后的值
That's just something to have in mind in case you're designing basically a
这些都是在设计无损预测和
predictive loss, a predictive lossless and lossy image compression.
无损图像压缩时需要记住的
If you want to have quantization, remember, you cannot use anything in
如果想要做量化处理 那么请记住 在图像压缩时不能使用
image compression that the decoder doesn't have.
解码器无法获得的信息
As an encoder, you have only, you are only allowed to use things that
对于编码器而言 它只能利用解码器所能获得的信息
the decoder is going to see. Otherwise, this basically is not a
如果不这样做 这个系统就不对称
symmetric system, and it won't work. So, that's just the only thing to have in
它也不会很好的运作 因此 这是大家唯一需要记住的地方
mind. And as I say JPEG-LS includes a
正如我所说的 JPEG-LS中包含量化
quantization. So this is the basic underlying idea of
这就是无损预测编码或者
lossless, predictive coding, or lossy, but with
以及有一定误差的编码方法背后的思想
control, loss. Now, that's not the only way that we can
我们用来预测的方法并不只有这一种
do prediction. And basically MPEG, which is the standard
还有MPEG 它是视频压缩的标准
for video compression, is also based on prediction.
也是基于预测来实现压缩的
But now, I have actually multiple frames. So remember in video, we have let's say
不过 这里有很多的帧 想一下视频中 一秒钟有三十帧
30 frames a second. So in order to predict, for example,
为了完成预测 我们举个例子
this frame, I can use past frames to predict it.
对于这个帧 可以用前面几个帧来预测它
And, the basic idea is very simple. If I'm filming a scene that is completely
基本思想很简单 如果拍摄的场景是完全静止的
static, then every frame will be identical to the previous frame.
那么每一帧都会和之前的帧一模一样
And MPEG is trying to take advantage of that.
MPEG会试图利用这个性质
It's trying to say, okay, let's just look at the region in an image
它会试图关注图像中的一个区域
and let's see if that region, this basic constant, and you can do it in
看看这块区域是不是恒定不变的 这可以用很多方法实现
multiple fashions, and we're not going to discuss all the
我们不会详细讨论MPEG是如何实现这些的
details behind MPEG. But for example, you can actually say
不过 作为一个例子
okay, I'm going to see if this region here; if there is a similar region around
大家可以看一下这块区域 观察它附近有没有相似的区域
it, it doesn't have to be exactly at the same place, it can be around it.
并不一定是完全相同的位置 可以是在它的周围
It can basically look for similar regions in previous frames, maybe in only in one
MPEG可以在之前的几帧里寻找相似的区域
frame, maybe only in three frames before me, it's going to look for similar
或许是一帧 或许是三帧 它会去寻找相似的区域
regions and it's going to basically also try to encode only the error.
然后只编码那些误差
So it's going to do prediction in time. Okay?
它会做时间上的预测
And it's a very, very simple idea, and that works extremely well.
这种想法很简单 而且非常实用
We know that MPEG actually compresses a lot,
我们知道MPEG能够压缩很多空间
thanks to the fact that for example, this is a good example. The only thing that is
因为有这样一个事实 举个很好的例子 在这个视频里
moving in this video is me. The whole background is constant.
只有我一个人在动 而整个背景是一直保持不变的
So, if you pick blocks in the background, you're going to find in previous frames
如果你在背景中取一块区域 你可以在之前的几帧里
basically identical blocks and then the prediction error will be zero and that's
找到一样的区域 这样 预测误差就会变成零
great for the encoder. So here is an example with basically we
这对编码器来说是件好事 我们再举个例子
have the same image that we had before but basically we have two frames of that
这是之前看过的图像 不过这里有两帧这样的图像
image one and two and we do a very simple prediction here, which basically we say,
图像一和图像二 我们做一个简单的预测
okay, the second image is identical to the first image.
我们预测第二个图像和第一个图像相同
If there is not a lot of motion, we see that prediction is really, really good.
如果图像中没有太多的移动 那这会是一个非常好的预测
Most of the time it's zero, as we have seen before for the special predictor.
就像之前看到的空间上的预测器一样 多数情况下 预测误差会是零
This is a temporary predictor. Once again, every pixel here is predicted
这是一个时域预测器 我们预测每一个像素
as to be identical to the pixel in the same position in the previous image.
都和前一幅图像中相同位置的像素点一样
We can be smarter. We can look for that pixel in a region
我们可以更聪明一些 在那个点附近找相同的像素点
around it, and then we are going to encode both the value and the offset So,
然后再同时编码像素值和偏移量
did I find it to the left, or did I find it,
这样就知道是在左边 或其他某个地方找到了相同的像素点
eh, eh, downwards. But here it was the simplest possible
但是这例子是最简单的
thing. Just basically exactly in the same
在一样的位置找到相同的像素点
position. And this is the difference, and this is
这是上面两幅图像的差
the distribution of the error. So basically, if I know this frame.
这是误差的分布图 所以 如果知道了这一帧图像
I'm going to be able to reproduce this frame very, very efficiently by copying
那么就能通过复制前一帧 并加上相应的误差值
the previous frame, and adding the, this image, which is the error image.
高效地产生这一帧图像
Copying the previous frame is free, because I already have it.
因为解码器已经有了前一帧图像 所以复制它不需要占用额外的空间
The decoder array has it. And compressing this, because it's so
因为误差集中在零附近
concentrated in zero, it's really, really very efficient with techniques with
用霍夫曼编码就可以高效地压缩它
Huffman coding. I add these two images, I get this one,
把这两幅图像相加就能得到这幅图像
and then I continue to the next frame. And of course, if there is a lot of
然后再计算下一帧图像 但如果图像中有很多移动
motion, the error image won't be as simple, but hopefully it will be simple
那么误差图就不会这么简单 但我们希望它能足够简单
enough that Huffman can take advantages of it.
这样霍夫曼编码就能够利用这一点
And this is the basic block diagram of MPEG, or video compression techniques.
这是MPEG或者视频压缩技术的基本流程图
It's very similar to what we have seen for JPEG.
它和JPEG的流程图很相似
It basically has DCT, quantization, variable length coding like half man.
它用到了离散余弦变换、量化和像霍夫曼编码这种不等长编码方法
It only has this additional component here, which is basically encoding the
它只是额外添加了这个模块 用来编码时域的预测误差
prediction in time. So it's the one that takes care of doing
这个模块负责对图像移动的预测
this motion estimation and saying, okay, I want to take this block from a region
使用之前图像的一个区域作为预测
in the past. But the basic structure is the samic
但是基本结构是一样的
structure, plus this that takes into account that
加上这个模块来处理时域的预测
I'm not compressing just one image, and basically compressing multiple
并不是只压缩一幅图像 而是压缩很多幅图像
frames, and many of them are very similar.
而且很多是相似的
So, once again, predictive coding. Here actually is a combination between
再次提一下预测编码 这里利用了
the techniques that we have seen for JPEG,
在JPEG中使用到的技术
and the techniques that we have seen for predictive coding.
和在预测编码中用到的技术
Both together produce MPEG. With this, we basically have concluded
两者相结合产生了MPEG 我们已经总结了
the basic underlying concepts of image and video compression.
图像和视频压缩背后的概念
So we have discussed JPEG, we have discussed JPEG-LS, and we have discussed
我们讨论了JPEG 讨论了JPEG-LS和MPEG
MPEG. We did transform, we did predictive
我们利用了一些变换 做了预测编码
coding, we did quantization, we did basically Huffman coding.
我们用到了量化和霍夫曼编码
The whole building blocks of compression, which is what we basically use daily in
我们讨论了压缩的每一个模块 在图像和视频处理中每天都会用到这些
image and video processing. In the next video, which is going to be a
下一个视频是附加视频
bonus video, if you have time, I recommend you to watch it.
如果你有时间 我建议你看一下这个视频
I'm going to describe very briefly what's called run length coding, just to
我会大致介绍一下游程编码 这样你会有一个全面的了解
complete the picture. But, if you don't have time, you can just
但是如果你没有时间 你可以跳过这个视频
skip that video, and next week go into the next unit.
下一周我们将进入下一个单元
Thank you very much.
非常感谢